Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Company Offices, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated; 1920-2000; 86 boxes plus oversize containers
  - Agency in Force Office, 1850, 1920-1994 and undated
    - Manual of Instructions, 1975-1977 and undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Letter from B. W. Kennedy - legal competency of minors, 1937 (Box 8)
    - Letter from B. W. Kennedy - regarding claims signed by practitioners other than licensed physicians, 1955 (Box 8)
    - NCM weekly premium receipt book, unknown agent, 1954-1955 (Box 8)
    - Memos and letters, 1992 May-Dec. (Box 8)
    - Binder of home addresses, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Binder of memos, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Personnel binder: transfers and terminations, 1991-1992 (Box 8)
      [Removed to Personnel Subseries.]
    - You and Your Company binder, after 1965 (Box 9)
    - Memos and letters, 1989 Jan.-1991 July, 4 binders (Box 9)
    - General ledger, Mr. McClinton, 1971-1979 (Box 10)
    - Blank form - application for life insurance, circa 1994 (Box 10)
    - Industrial agent contract, undated (Box 10)
    - List of 1968-1969 memoranda contents, and memos, 1968 Jan.-1973 Nov., 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Memos, 1968 Jan.-1969 July (Box 11)
    - Office Workers Union contract, 1952 (Box 11)
    - Ordinary agent's contract (special), undated (Box 11)
    - Regular ordinary agent's contract, undated (Box 11)
    - North Carolina Mutual Life [Raleigh] policy, 1850 with letter attached, 1969, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
      Mailed to NC Mutual's offices in 1969 by an executive in Baltimore, this life insurance policy was sold by an insurance organization in Raleigh by the same name of NC Mutual, which was organized in the 1840s and disbanded in the 1860s. A blank life insurance policy specifically for slaves printed by this same company can be found in the Charles Hunter Papers in the Rubenstein Library at Duke. It is not known what connection, if any, this company had with the subsequent NC Mutual founded in Durham in 1898.
    - Life insurance policies, 1921-1926, 3 folders; box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV3)
    - Matted life insurance policy, 1941, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV3)
      [Some of the materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents should be photocopied before being handled.]
    - Policies, 1921-1926, 3 folders; box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
    - Laminated policies, 1913, 1919, 1935, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
    - One million and a quarter drive chart, mortgages to go to Century Life, 1919, 1927, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
    - Training records and reports, 1962-1963, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV5)
    - Ledger, 1967-1986, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV6)
    - General ledger, 1982 Apr.-1984 Dec., box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV7)
    - A Birds-eye View of the Manager's Job, undated, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Blank policy, circa 1952, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Blank Policies, undated; 2 folders (Box 187)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes whole life, term life, joint whole life, graded premium whole life, economatic whole life, endowment insurance, retirement income endowment, mortgage policy-decreasing term life, juvenile modified whole life, juvenile whole life, juvenile endowment insurance, assorted industrial life policies, assorted hospitalization policies
  - Auditing Office, 1904-1905, 1922-1950, 1972-1987 and undated; 1970s-1980s
    Includes files relating to audits of NCM and its district offices, as well as material from the NCM Audit Committee. Audits were conducted by outside firms such as Deloitte, Haskins, and Sells and Ernst and Ernst.
    - Accountants and other correspondence, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Accounting audits, NCM, 1983-1987 (Box 11)
    - BC Audit Committee, 1980, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Deloitte, Haskins, and Sells:
      - Financial statement reports, 1981-1983 (Box 11)
      - NCM reports, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
      - Reports for NCM, 1981-1985, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Ernst and Ernst: CPA review of NCM, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
    - Internal auditors home office audits, 1980 (Box 11)
    - NCM Audit committee: (Box 12)
      - Agendas, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
      - Meetings, 1977-1985, 10 folders (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous documents, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
    - NCM internal audits, 1974-1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - PA audit, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Regular audits, 1980 (Box 13)
    - Financial statements and data, 1904-1905, 1922-1944, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
    - Financial statements, underwriters' pocket charts, death claims paid, 1922-1950, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
    - Financial statements, ordinary mortality experience statements, NIA questionnaire, 1927-1941, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
    - Ernst and Ernst checklist, undated, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV9)
  - Controller, 1945-2001 and undated
    The Office of the Controller is in charge of coordinating, planning, and reporting on financial activities, including bookkeeping, accounting, and financial reporting. The material in this subseries consists of the Report of the Controller to the Board of Directors for NCM, ranging from 1986-2001. Also contains annual reports, annual statements, and Bonds and Stocks Owned statements.
    - Controller position, staffing, duties, 1960s (Box 13)
    - NCM federal income tax return, 1995, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Report of the Controller, 1986-2001, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Abstracts from the Tenth Annual Statement, 1908 (Box 14)
    - Annual reports, 1963, 1987-2003, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Annual statements, 1945-1967, 1978-1988, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Bonds and stocks owned, 1945-1978, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Ratings and rankings from Best's and National Underwriter, 1964-1986 (Box 14)
    - Report of the Controller, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Annual statement, 1960, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
  - Corporate Planning, 1947-1952, 1958-1981 and undated; 9 boxes
    Contains detailed materials on the research, planning, execution, and move to the new Mutual Plaza home office, 1964-1967, including blueprints for the home office and the Chatham annex. Also includes plans for long-range planning such as organizational and management restructuring; business plans by company department; reports, manuals for the functions and duties of home office organization; reviews of data processing, and correspondence with management consulting firms and other companies. Additionally, contains alphabetized files of general correspondence, as well as solicitations to NCM for donations from organizations such as National Urban League, Nursing Association, 4-H, and the Hampton Institute and other higher education entities.
    Also present are materials and operations manuals for several other African American-run life insurance companies such as Jackson Mutual Life (1947), General American Life Insurance, and Equitable of Iowa.
    There is one file in box 20 housing a small group of interesting speeches given by Goodloe, Spaulding, and others for a variety of occasions including racial conflicts during the 1960s, and a copy of Kennedy's Historical Sketch of NCM history.
    Includes information regarding Murray Marvin (one of the directors of Corporate Planning) during his time at both Jackson Mutual and NC Mutual.
    Note: The structure of the Corporate Planning department changed several times over the course of NC Mutual's history. Corporate Planning and Public Relations merged under Murray Marvin in 1967 and was reorganized into Planning and Communications around 1976.
    - Corporate Planning files (Box 15-24)
    - Floor plans, undated, 2 folders; box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
    - Clipping, 1966, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
    - Monthly review of office construction and costs, 1965, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Clippings, 1970, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Display panel and blueprints, 1952-1958, box size: 24x36 inches (Box OV10)
    - Blueprint, Mutual Plaza (?), circa 1960s, box size: 24x36 inches (Box OV10)
    - Very large blueprints, 24x36", 5 items (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Executive Committee [RESTRICTED], 1922-2003 and undated; 1972-1989
    Mainly pertains to business conducted by the Executive Committee, a standing committee of the Board of Directors, which is made up of a minimum of five Directors, at least one of which is required to be an outside Director. Material from the Salary Committee, another standing committee of the Board, is also included in this subseries. The Salary Committee consists of five of the Directors, one of whom must be the President of the company.
    [Subseries is restricted for 25 years from date of last created folder, or 2028; until that date, written permission must be given by donor before contents can be accessed.]
    - Beechwood Cemetery, 1939-1966, 1998-2003, and undated (Box 25)
    - Housing project for home office employees, 1948 (Box 25)
    - Minutes of Budget Control Committee, 1928-1944 (Box 25)
    - Mrs. W.D. Hill, 1945 (Box 25)
    - Bessie Whitted mortgage, 1952 (Box 25)
    - D.C. Deans, Richmond City Council, 1952 (Box 25)
    - Board of Directors, 1927-1952 (Box 25)
    - Gaillard correspondence, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Committees, 1941-1972 (Box 25)
    - Great Lakes region, 1972-1975 (Box 25)
    - Good Citizen Life Insurance Company, 1973 (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1922-1938 and undated (Box 25)
    - Response to Business Week's Upheaval in Life Insurance, 1984 (Box 25)
    - Minute book of Budget Control Committee, 1928-1944 (Box 25)
    - Salary Committee:
      - Hay Associates, 1978-1986 (Box 25)
      - Hay Associates compensation study, 1985 (Box 25)
      - Clerical salary adjustments, 1972-1984 (Box 25)
      - Nominating Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 25)
      - Merit increases and promotion recommendations, 1987-1988 (Box 25)
      - Agency regional bonuses, 1976-1990 (Box 25)
      - Board meeting, 1983 (Box 25)
      - Data processing job descriptions, 1979-1989 and undated (Box 25)
      - Performance standards worksheets, 1973-1975 (Box 25)
      - Annual Statement Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 25)
      - Employee retirement dates, 1975-1981 (Box 25)
      - Net annualized premiums, 1975-1976 (Box 25)
      - Notes, charts and memoranda, 1978-1991 and undated (Box 25)
      - Salary information, 1979 (Box 25)
      - Salary charts, 1980-1983 (Box 25)
      - Clerical salary adjustments, 1973-1988 (Box 25)
      - Salary increases, senior officers and directors, (J. W. Goodloe on cover), 1977 (Box 25)
    - Salary Committee: (Box 26)
      - Charity fund committee, 1931-1932 (Box 26)
      - John C. Blackman claim, 1972 (Box 26)
      - Salary Study, 1956 (Box 26)
      - Memoranda, charts, guides, and notes, 1988-1989 (Box 26)
      - Notes, memoranda, and charts, 1986-1988 and undated (Box 26)
      - Agendas and memoranda, 1989-1990 and undated (Box 26)
      - Officer and administrative salaries, 1969-1985 and undated (Box 26)
      - Charts and memoranda, 1987-1988 (Box 26)
      - Proposed budget, 1987 (Box 26)
      - Salary forms, undated (Box 26)
      - Salary breakdown by department, 1977-1986 (Box 26)
      - News clippings, 1985 (Box 26)
      - Annual statement and proposed budget, 1985-1986 (Box 26)
      - Home office salary schedules, 1924-1964 (Box 26)
      - Salary memos, 1926-1958 (Box 26)
      - Salary adjustment notes and charts, 1989 (Box 26)
      - Salaries, 1978-1981, 1987, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Salary charts, 1976-1981 (Box 26)
      - Salary adjustments, 1969-1989 (Box 26)
      - Salary increases, early retirements, position cuts, 1989-1990 (Box 26)
      - Salary increases, etc, 1981-1988 (Box 26)
    - Salary Committee: (Box 27)
      - Salary increases, etc, 1981-1988, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - Salaries, 1960s-1970s (Box 27)
      - Salary increases, 1980-1982, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Officers' salaries, 1946-1964, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
    - Officers' salaries and operations analysis, 1974, 1989, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
    - Drives letter, 1922 Feb. 1, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Envelope with notes and directions, undated, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Good Citizens Life Insurance Co. agent report, 1973, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Financial statements of other companies, income and investment table, 1952-1955, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Salary expenses and increases by district, 1980-1985, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Salary worksheets, reports, and bonus projections, 1977-1980, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    - Assets and stocks of life insurance companies, salary study, 1969, box size: 24x36 inches (Box OV10)
  - Facilities, 1950-1966, 1990-1998 and undated
    Contains material concerning the home office at Mutual Plaza. It includes photos of the construction and dedication of Mutual Plaza, as well as blueprints, manuals, guides, and reservation forms. It also includes a Department of Housing and Urban Development (DHUD) award for building design. Arranged in original order as received.
    - The Whetstone, Mutual Plaza issues, 1963-1964 (Box 28)
    - New home office - programs, promotional material, and invitation, 1963-1966 (Box 28)
    - Moving to Mutual Plaza manual, 1966 (Box 28)
    - Construction of Mutual Plaza photos, 1963-1964 and undated, 12 folders (Box 28)
    - Dedication - Mutual Plaza, 1950-1966 and undated, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - HVAC evaluation, 1990 (Box 28)
    - NCM building layout, undated (Box 28)
    - Stressteel post-tensioning publication, after 1966 (Box 28)
    - Facility reservations and related forms, 1994-1998, 4 folders (Box 29)
    - Department of Housing and Urban Development: Honor Awards for Design Excellence, 1966 (Box 29)
    - Clippings, 1966, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
    - Floor plans and blue prints, 1963-1964, box size: 24x36 inches (Box OV10)
  - Medical Department, 1922, 1955, 1978, 1984-1990, 2002; 1980s-1990s
    Materials include a history of the department, which was established by Dr. A.T. Moore in 1916 and disbanded after 2002, as well as print material produced for health campaigns, and biographical information on directors Dr. Charles D. Watts and Dr. John T. Daniel. Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title. Other archival records and memorabilia on medical topics and health campaigns can be found in the Printed Material, Publicity, and Memorabilia Series.
    - Curriculum Vitae, Dr. Watts and miscellaneous Medical Department material, 1955, 1978, 1984-1986 (Box 29)
    - Daniel, John T., M.D., Senior Vice President position description, 1987 (Box 29)
    - Employee Wellness Program, 2002 (Box 29)
    - Medical Bulletin: Tuberculosis, 1922 Feb. 3, from Director Dr. Donnell, two pages (Box 29)
    - Medical Staff's Agency Ordinary Series Product and User's Manual binder, 1993-1999 (Box 29)
    - NCM History of the Medical Department: 1916-1988, circa 1988 (Box 29)
    - Raising Healthy Children, Dr. Alvin Poussaint, 1990, talk, includes photo of his visit to Durham (Box 29)
    - Swat That Fly, circa 1920s, health campaign circular from Director, illustrated (ink) (Box 29)
    - Sign, undated, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
  - Office of the President, 1903-2002 and undated; 1950s-1990s
    This subseries consists of material from the offices and files of five of NCM's nine presidents: William J. Kennedy, Jr., Asa T. Spaulding, Sr., Joseph W. Goodloe, William J. Kennedy, III, and Bert Collins. The contents relate mainly to the periods during which these presidents held the office, though in some cases there is material from previous positions they held within NCM and apart from the company. Much of the material includes files relating to the execution of company business, correspondence, and personnel matters. The majority of the material in the subseries originates from the offices of William Kennedy III and Bert Collins.
    Files in the Office of the President Subseries are restricted for 25 years from the last year of each presidency. Permission to access these records must be granted by NC Mutual in writing prior to use.
    Personnel files found in this series have been separated and are closed for 75 years from the date of creation of material, or 2074.
    Please contact the Rubenstein staff for more information.
    - William J. Kennedy, Jr., 1903-1968; 1940s-1960s; 5 boxes
      Served as President of NC Mutual from 1952-1958. Much of the contents of this subseries comprises the materials that Kennedy, Jr. used to document the history of North Carolina Mutual, as well as the wide variety of historical sketches he produced. Other material in this subseries relates to general company business from his tenure at NCM both as the Corporate Secretary and as President, including a letter of support for Pauli Murray's admission to the New York State Bar Association in 1948. Additionally, there is material relating to his tenure as the President of the Bankers Fire and Casualty Insurance Company.
      [Some of the material found in box 33 is fragile and should be handled with care. Contact reference archivist before using, as material may need photocopying before use.]
      - Bankers Fire and Casualty Insurance Company
        - Bankers Fire and Casualty:
          - 1929, 1962-1968, and undated, 2 folders (Box 30)
          - By-laws, WJK resignation, and miscellaneous documents, 1960-1968 (Box 30)
          - Christmas message, 1963-1967 (Box 30)
          - Correspondence and miscellaneous business, 1954, 1958-1965, 1967, and undated, 2 folders (Box 30)
          - Executive Committee, 1963-1968 (Box 30)
          - Expansion program, 1956-1962 (Box 30)
          - Minutes, Executive Committee, and Board, 1964-1968 (Box 30)
          - Statements of Condition, 1960-1968 (Box 30)
        - Bankers Fire and Casualty:
          - 1965-1968 and undated (Box 32)
          - 1921, 1926, 1963-1968 (Box 32)
          - Personnel File, 1965-1967 (Box 32)
      - NCM Company Business
        - Century Life Insurance Company, 1927 and undated (Box 30)
        - Golden Anniversary program, 1949 (Box 30)
        - Letter of recommendation for Pauli Murray to the N.Y. Bar from W. J. Kennedy, Jr., 1948 (Box 30)
        - Letter regarding unemployment from Alabama Department of Industrial Relations, 1946 June 1 (Box 30)
        - Liberia Today, 1956 (Box 30)
        - Minutes from meetings of the Actuarial staff, 1957-1959 (Box 30)
        - Miscellaneous documents, 1965 and undated (Box 30)
        - Miscellaneous NCM business, 1924, 1927, 1933, 1944-1955, 1959-1961, 1964-1966, and undated, 2 folders (Box 30)
        - Mortgage loans, 1944, 1950-1956, and undated (Box 30)
        - National Association of Insurance Commissioners, 1949-1953 (Box 31)
        - NCM Real Estate, 1931-1953 (Box 31)
        - NIA Convention, 1966 (Box 31)
        - North Carolina state insurance laws, 1949-1950 (Box 31)
        - Other insurers' policies, 1957 and undated (Box 31)
        - Requests for deferment to the Selective Service Draft Board, 1942-1944 (Box 31)
        - Speeches, 1950, 1953-1965 (Box 31)
        - Afro-American insurance companies, 1927-1930 and undated (Box 32)
        - Annual reports of banking institutions owned and operated by Negroes, 1944-1960 (Box 32)
        - Board of Directors meetings binder, 1925, 1950-1964 (Box 32)
        - Correspondence between Abner Lee and "Lee," 1965 Apr. and undated (Box 32)
        - Durham Herald clipping regarding 15th annual National Negro Insurance Association (NIA) convention, 1935 May 22 (Box 32)
        - Financial statements, banks, and savings and loan associations, Durham, 1955 (Box 32)
        - Forms committee, 1946, 1949-1953, and undated (Box 32)
        - Mortgage loans, 1952, 1957-1959, and undated (Box 32)
        - Miscellaneous historical papers, 1942, 1947, circa 1959 (Box 32)
        - NCM annual statements folder, 1909-1910, 1914-1915, 1918-1955, 1957-1965 (Box 32)
        - Officers' salaries from various insurance companies, 1955-1956 (Box 32)
        - Population statistics, 1943-1965 and undated (Box 32)
        - Records of insurance companies owned by Negroes, 1943-1958 (Box 32)
        - Sales drives - Agents' conferences, 1919, 1923, and undated (Box 32)
      - NCM History Project
        - A Brief Outline History of the Organization, Growth, and Development of the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1898-1931 by Asa T. Spaulding (Box 31)
        - A Symbol of Progress: 1898-1966, History of the NC Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1966, 5 folders (Box 31)
        - Biographical sketches of E.R. Merrick and Aaron McDuffie Moore, circa 1967 and undated (Box 31)
        - Correspondence with N.J. Board of Education, 1954, 1963 (Box 31)
        - Dr. J.H. Taylor, consultant - history and correspondence, 1960-1967 (Box 31)
        - History of J.M. Avery and other NCM history and business info, 1914, 1931, 1942-1945, and undated (Box 31)
        - NCM Historical Sketches and Supplements, 1930, 1935, 1939, 1944-1945, 1955, 1961, and undated (Box 32)
        - The North Carolina Mutual Story - A Symbol of Progress: 1899-1966(the founding of NC Mutual), handwritten manuscript, 1966, 9 folders (Box 33)
        - History of NC Mutual: (Box 34)
          - Biography of founders and other material for writing NCM history, 1959 (Box 34)
          - Miscellaneous reproduced photos and other material, 1904, 1943-1959, and undated, 2 folders (Box 34)
        - Miscellaneous photos and documents for the NC Mutual history project, 1903, 1908-1910, 1928, 1937, 1948, 1963-1965, and undated (Box 34)
          - John Merrick biographical notes, 1932-1943 and undated (Box 34)
        - Miscellaneous photos and loose materials, 1912, circa 1950, and undated (Box 34)
        - Miss S.E. Bailey, consultant - NC Mutual history, 1960 (Box 34)
        - Mr. W.J. Kennedy, Jr. to Mr. John A. Spaulding, 1960-1963, 1966 (Box 34)
        - Mrs. G.P. Lipscomb - NC Mutual history project, 1966 (Box 34)
        - NCM history and historical sketches, circa 1934, 1944, 1959, and undated (Box 34)
          Several drafts of the NCM historical sketch is also found in Kennedy's son's papers, in the William Kennedy III Subseries.
        - NCM History Committee:
          - 1962-1970 (Box 34)
          - Illustration labels, 1969 and undated (Box 34)
          - Memos to directors, 1959-1969 (Box 34)
          - "History of other Life Companies" correspondence file, 1959-1967 (Box 34)
        - University Press - UNC-Chapel Hill - Mr. W.J. Kennedy, Jr., 1963-1965 (Box 34)
    - Asa T. Spaulding, 1932-1969 and undated
      Spaulding served as President of NCM from 1959-1967. Mainly includes speeches and press releases, as well as some material relating to company business. Much more information can be found in the Asa T. and Elna Spaulding Papers held in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
      - A. T. Spaulding biographical sketches, 1933, 1937, 1956, 1961, 1968, and undated (Box 32)
      - Newspaper clippings, circa 1959 (Box 32)
      - Press release, circa 1957 (Box 32)
      - 7th annual G.W. Cox Sales for NCM 60th anniversary, 1959 (Box 35)
      - 50th and 60th anniversaries, 1949, 1959-1960 (Box 35)
      - 60th anniversary and miscellaneous newspapers, 1954-1961 and undated (Box 35)
      - A Christmas Wish by A.T. Spaulding, undated (Box 35)
      - A Message by A.T. Spaulding, 1934 (Box 35)
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1963 and undated (Box 35)
      - Histories of Negro Insurance, 1943 and undated (Box 35)
      - Membership certificate from National Defense Executive Reserve, 1959 July 1 (Box 35)